Guide to the John Francis Hamtramck Papers, 1757-1862
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
John Francis Hamtramck papers 1757-1862
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Hamtramck, John Francis, 1798-1858.
2.0 linear feet Extent: 2,630 Items
U.S. Indian agent, Army officer during the Mexican War; from Shepherdstown, West Virginia. Correspondence and other papers, relating to Hamtramck's activities as agent to the Osage Indians, to troop movements, army discipline, supplies, and other matters during the Mexican War, and to the Hamtramck family. Includes letters of Hamtramck's father, John Francis Hamtramck, and of Shepherdstown merchant Walter Selby, Hamtramck's father-in-law. Correspondents include Elias Boudinot, William Clark, George Clinton, Pierre Couteau, Caleb Cushing, John H. Eaton, John Hancock, R. M. T. Hunter, George Izard, John Jay, Elias Kent Kane, Henry Knox, Arthur St. Clair, and Jesse Burgess Thomas.
hamtramckjohn
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The John Francis Hamtramck Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in 1948, 1956, 1963, 1968, 1971, and 1972.
Biographical Note
John Francis Hamtramck (1798-1858) was a U.S. Indian agent, Army officer during the Mexican War; from Shepherdstown, West Virginia.
Collection Overview
Correspondence and other papers, relating to Hamtramck's activities as agent to the Osage Indians, to troop movements, army discipline, supplies, and other matters during the Mexican War, and to the Hamtramck family. Includes letters of Hamtramck's father, John Francis Hamtramck, and of Shepherdstown, West Virginia merchant Walter Selby, Hamtramck's father-in-law. Correspondents include Elias Boudinot, William Clark, George Clinton, Pierre Couteau, Caleb Cushing, John H. Eaton, John Hancock, R. M. T. Hunter, George Izard, John Jay, Elias Kent Kane, Henry Knox, Arthur St. Clair, and Jesse Burgess Thomas.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Boudinot, Elias, 1740-1821; Clark, William; Clinton, George, 1739-1812; Couteau, Pierre; Cushing, Caleb, 1800-1879; Eaton, John Henry, 1790-1856; Hancock, John, 1737-1793; Hunter, R. M. T. (Robert Mercer Taliaferro), 1809-1887; Izard, George, 1777-1828; Jay, John, 1745-1829; Kane, Elias Kent, 1794-1835; Knox, Henry, 1750-1806; St. Clair, Arthur, 1734-1818; Thomas, Jesse Burgess, 1777-1853; United States. Army -- Officers; Indians of North America -- Government relations; Osage Indians; Merchants -- West Virginia -- Shepherdstown; Mexican War, 1846-1848
Contents of Collection
- John Francis Hamtramck Papers, 1757-1862, (6 boxes)
  Volumes in Box 5 include three commonplace books, an account book, a book of sales, and a household inventory list.
  - Correspondence and Papers, 1757-1829 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence and Papers, 1830-1843 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence and Papers, 1846-1849 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence and Papers, 1848 Jan.-June and undated (Box 4)
  - Volumes (Box 5)
  - Oversize: 1825-1847, Feb. (Box 6)
  - Oversize military papers, 1847, Mar-June (Box 6)
  - Oversize military papers, 1847, July-1848 and undated (Box 6)
  - Oversize list of return of first regiment, 1847 Oct. (Box 6)
  - Oversize materials (Oversize-box 47)
  - Oversize materials (Opaperfolder 1)
  - Bound manuscript volume (Volume F:5354)
  - Bound manuscript volume, 1833-1835 (Volume F:6761)
  - Bound manuscript volume, 1833-1837 (Volume F:6762)